Guide to the Barbara Rubin Papers, 1964-2014.
Rubin, Barbara Papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Barbara Rubin Papers, 1964-2014.
8612
Barbara. Rubin
.5 cubic feet
Photographs, printed materials, photocopies, and mimeographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of play and film scripts, correspondence, ephemera and photographic prints.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Filmmaker and writer Barbara Rubin (1945-1980), born in Cambria Heights, Queens, NY, was 17 when, not long discharged from a Connecticut institution, she began working for Jonas Mekas at the Film-Makers' Cinematheque in New York in 1963. Using a 16mm camera lent to her by Mekas, she began filming Christmas On Earth in the Lower East Side apartment of Tony Conrad and John Cale at 56 Ludlow Street, where Sterling Morrison and Lou Reed later lived (and, first recorded "All Tomorrow's Parties"). Christmas On Earth is sexually explicit to a degree surprising for its time. The film - more technically a cinematic "performance" - typically screened as per her instructions on two projectors with a contemporary rock radio soundtrack. During the next few years she was an active participant in the New York underground art scene, where she introduced Allen Ginsberg to Bob Dylan, and Andy Warhol to the Velvet Underground, at whose Exploding Plastic Inevitable performances she both participated and projected her film. Rubin filmed the Velvets in an early performance in 1965; however, the footage is now lost. She drew up plans for sequels to her film but these were never filmed; one of her synopses (which she sent to Walt Disney), proposed a plot wherein French author Jean Genet (playing himself, but as a Bowery bum) is rescued from his situation by fairies. While there were a handful of additional screenings before the end of the 1960s, soon after joining a Hasidic sect, Rubin instructed Mekas to destroy her film. He didn't, and later she agreed that Christmas On Earth could again be shown, as it has been regularly since 1983. After giving up filmmaking she married and moved to France. She died in 1980, age 35, after giving birth to her sixth child.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of play and film scripts, correspondence, ephemera and photographic prints.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Rubin, Barbara.; Mekas, Jonas, 1922-.; Scherman, Tony.; Warhol, Andy, 1928-1987.
Titles:
Christmas on earth.
Subjects:
Experimental films.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Contracts and correspondence
Series II. Film scripts and manuscripts
Series III. Fliers and programs
Series IV. Photographs
Series V. Press Material
CONTAINER LIST
- Contracts and correspondence, 1964-2003
  - Contracts, Undated
    - Agreement for use of Royal Albert Hall, Undated; 1 leaf folded to 6 pages. Print and typescript (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Contract for the evening of Friday, June 17, 1966. Misspelling of "Andy Warhole"
    - Special, Special Special Addition To The Special Letter, Undated; 8 pages; Mimeographed with orange cover. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1964-2003
    - Letter addressed to Arlene McElroy, Arthur Knight, Hollis Albert, and Playboy, Undated; Rubin, Barbara; 1 page; Mimeographed. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Annotated along left side, "S.S.
    - Autograph letter to Jonas Mekas, Undated; Rubin, Barbara; 1 page; Handwritten single page that goes onto verso (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Beginning, "Jonas, I was here to say hello even thou…"
    - Autograph letter signed to Jonas Mekas, 1966-05; Rubin, Barbara; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 2)
      I love your language I love you… Written on the verso of a completed questionnaire for the Filmmakers' Cinematheque
    - Letter signed to Jonas Mekas from Tony Scherman, 2003-02-24; 1 page; Photocopy of typed letter. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Concerning an interview about Warhol and film by Rubin
    - Autograph letter signed to Jonas Mekas, Undated; Rubin, Barbara; 2 pages; Handwritten on lined paper (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Begins, "Dear Jonas Spent a lovely thrill in the country…"
    - Autograph letter signed to Jonas Mekas, 1964-01-24; Rubin, Barbara; 4 pages; Handwritten on onionskin paper. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "Dear Jonas, I just saw your letter to Sidney and I…"
    - Autograph letter signed to Jonas Mekas, Undated; Rubin, Barbara; 1 page; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "Dear Jonas, We've comes and gones…"
    - Envelope addressed to Jonas Mekas, 1964-01-23; Rubin, Barbara (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Autograph letter signed to Jonas Mekas, Undated; Rubin, Barbara; 1 page; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "Dear Jonas - I just heard Rosebud committed herself…"
    - Autograph letter signed to Jonas Mekas, Undated; Rubin, Barbara; 1 page; Handwritten with old tape on both sides of the paper (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "Jonas This is a special addition to Allen…"
- Film scripts and manuscripts, 1965-1983
  - Film scripts, 1965-1973
    - Christmas on Earth, 1965
      - Trip Along With Christmas On Earth Continued Again Continuing Remains with Barbara Rubin 1966, Undated; 12 page mimeographed script, blue cover, with additional 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Trip Along With Christmas On Earth Continued Again Continuing Remains with Barbara Rubin 1966, Undated; Blue cover, front and back pages with Barbara Rubin autographed annotation on front and back (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Christmas on Earth Continued, 1965; 19 pages; Typescript on a variety of paper stocks (Box 1, Folder 5)
        First line of text is, "This is a scene
      - Christmas on Earth Continued, 1965; 31 pages; Mimeographed script in green text (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Christmas on Earth Continued, 1965; 16 pages; Carbonscript on a variety of paper stocks, string bound on right side (Box 1, Folder 7)
        First line of text: "Prologue ******"
      - Christmas On Earth Continued, 1965; 25 pages; Typescript in onionskin. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Other scripts, 1967-1973
      - Sidney Arthur, A Musical Comedy, 1967-07-18; Rubin, Barbara and Shirley Clarke; 6 pages; Photocopy of typescript film script (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Shooting Script for The Film The Broken Betrothal from the story by Rebbe Nachman of Breslov, 1973; 16 pages; Photocopied script (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Date from ms. note on top of first page
      - Emouna, 1972; 12 pages; Photocopied script (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manuscripts, 1965-1983
    Mainly undated.
    - Christmas on Earth, Undated
      - Christmas on Earth Continued Again… a chatter on the movie, Undated; 23 pages; Mimeographed prose piece (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Christmas on Earth Continued Again… a chatter on the movie, Undated; 23 pages; Mimeographed prose piece (Box 1, Folder 11)
        With annotation in red ink possibly in the hand of Barbara Rubin that reads, "M I C K E Y MOUSE
      - Christmas on Earth Continued Again… a chatter on the movie, Undated; 23 pages; Mimeographed prose piece (Box 1, Folder 11)
        With annotation in red ink possibly in the hand of Barbara Rubin that reads, "IDEAL."
      - A Personal Statement on the Movie Christmas on Earth Continued, 1965; 8 pages; Mimeographed (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Projection instructions for Christmas On Earth, Undated; 1 page; Mimeographed. Autographed on top right by Barbara Rubin (Box 1, Folder 12)
        As explained by Barbara Rubin
      - Projection instructions for Christmas On Earth, Undated; 1 page; Typescript with handwritten rental cost annotation on a backing page. Verso is Anthology stationary (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Projection instructions for Christmas On Earth, Undated; 1 page; Photocopy with rental cost annotation across top (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Projection instructions for Christmas On Earth, 1983; 1 page; Mimeographed (Box 1, Folder 12)
        As explained by Jonas Mekas
      - Notes about Christmas On Earth, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Written on Anthology Film Archives stationary, possibly in the hand of Jonas Mekas
      - Notes on Christmas On Earth, 1968-04; 1 page; Mimeographed (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Included with projection instructions
    - General, 1972-1983
      - We Invite You To The Screening of The First Film of Trilogy Emunah (Ruff Cut), 1972; 8 pages; Mimeographed pamphlet. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Listing of Rubin's films and description of a program to be presented with Gordon Ball, Undated; 2 pages; Manuscript on yellow lined paper. (Box 1, Folder 13)
        In Barbara Rubin's hand beginning, "I) Insert A + B
      - "These three pages received from Pam (xeroxer) April, 26, '83 She said she'll give me the whole ms.", 1983-04-26; 3 pages; Photocopied mimeograph with annotation on verso of third page (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Barbara Rubin and Gordon Ball, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Page 2 of only a two page typescript with heading, This page primarily concerns Ball
      - Ms. notes beginning, "6 in all Dylan Records…", Undated; Rubin, Barbara (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Single page handwritten note
      - Invoice from Film Lab for developing a Rubin film, 1964; 1 page; Missing top left of page (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Rubin film 16 mm b/w reversible silent print. Date from ms. annotation on bottom of page
      - Book of Formation (Sefer Yetzirah), Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Folder containing photocopied pages
- Fliers and programs, 1967-1983
  - Fliers, 1967
    - The Sixteenth of April Movement: RESIST, Undated; 1 page; Photocopied flier (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Flier for screenings at the Hyde Park Art Center featuring a write up about Christmas On Earth
    - Invitation for a reading and screening of Christmas On Earth, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      At The Film-maker's Cinematheque on March 5th
    - House of Seraphim Ltd., Undated; Flier (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Ms. annotation on bottom in black ink, "Shop belongs to Wendy Clarke + Barbara Rubin" and graphite annotation on top right, "Barbara Rubin"
    - Caterpillar Changes, 1967; Yellow and red color offset flier (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Butterfly Booboos, 1967; B/W photocopied flier (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Programs, Undated
    - Not Forgotten Series (Program1), Undated; 6 pages; Photocopied pamphlet. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      "Barbara Rubin (b. 1946 - d. 1981) Christmas On Earth" Program notes by Jonas Mekas
    - The Kitchen's screening of Christmas On Earth and Jean Genet's Un Chant D'Amour, 1983; 2 pages; Program (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Double Vision split between Barbara Rubin and Andy Warhol., Undated; 1 page; Mimeographed program announcement (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Film-Makers' Cinematheque
    - Expanded Cinema, Undated; 1 page; Mimeographed program announcement (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photographs, 1963-2013
  - Original photographs, 1963-2011
    - Vintage still from Christmas On Earth, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      With annotation on back inroad ink, "Christmas On Earth Barbara Rubin"
    - Barbara Rubin filming 'Allen for Alen' London June 1965., Undated; Ginsberg, Allen; Photocopy of photograph (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Portrait of a yon woman named Debbi, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      B/w photo print annotated on bottom left corner, "For Jonas Love and XXX's Debbi
    - Andy Warhol, 2011; Laser print of three frames (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Still from Barbara Rubin screen test ca. 1964
    - Caterpillar Changes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Annotation on back, "Caterpillar Changes / Matt Hoffman"
  - Exhibition Prints, 2012-2013
    52 Prints from the 2012/2013 Boo-Hooray and Anthology Film Archives show
    - Barbara Rubin: Christmas on Earth - Prints 1-56, 2012-2013 (Box 2)
      Missing 4.
- Press Material, 1965-2011
  - Periodicals, 1965-1967
    - Film Culture. No. 37. Summer, 1965, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Features an article by Jonas Mekas discussing Christmas On Earth
    - Film Culture. No. 44. Spring, 1967, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Features an article on the Caterpillar Changes festival that Barbara Rubin participated in
  - Clippings, 1965-2011
    - Short list of critical articles that mentions Barbara Rubin's Christmas On Earth, 1983; 1 page; Mimeographed. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      As reviewed by J. Hoberman in Village Voice, May 3, 1983 and Jonas Mekas' Notes On Barbara Rubin for The Collective for Living Cinema screening of April 29, 1983
    - Press clippings relating to Barbara Rubin, 1965-2011; 56 leaves; Original and photocopied (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Contains some duplicated material; some have minor ms. notes
  - Press releases, 1965-11-1983
    - The Kitchen's screening of Christmas On Earth and Jean Genet's Un Chant D'Amour, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Press Release
    - Special Announcement - Festival of Expanded Cinema, 1965-11; 1 page; Mimeographed press release (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Film You Will Be Seeing On December 23…, 1972; 2 pages; Mimeographed pamphlet. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Portion of Emunah screening invitation, apparently issued separately
    - Allen Ginsberg in Emunah: A Cooperative Collective Creation, 1972; 1 page; Photocopy (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Press release / program notes
    - Screening of films at The Underground, 1967-02-25; 1 page; Mimeograph on yellow paper (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Press release
    - Screening of films at The Underground, 1967-02-25; 1 page; Mimeograph on white paper (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - On Jan. 14, 1967 in the Golden Gate park in San Francisco there will be he ld a day of peace manifestation…, Undated; 1 page; Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Press release for a demonstration announcing appearances by Timothy Leary, Allen Ginsberg, Peter Orlovsky, Alan Watts, Gary Snyder, etc